Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 6 -- Letters to Franklin 1781-1782 Mss.B.F85inventory06
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaudoré, Augustin-François-Hugue Macé de
    His services in America since 1778, as Aide-de-camp to Col. Armand; only returned to France to re-establish his health; wishes to go back; begs Franklin to present the enclosed memoir [1p.] to the Minister, that he may obtain the commission of Captain and a donation for his trip over.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning a catalogue of the "Marquis de la Fayette's" cargo just received; sends it back with certain notes and marks. Mrs. Williams much better.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Bucaille, M -----
    Applies to Franklin to obtain a debt owing him by M. de Monneron, Engineer in the service to the United States; his embarrassing situation, due to the loss of such a considerable sum of money; encloses copy [1p.] of the two notes of indebtedness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Laurens, Henry. Nantes
    Advices received from England oblige him to start on his journey within forty-eight hours; begs Franklin to send his passport to Calais where it will overtake him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 11; A.L.S. 1p.; St. Clair, -----
    Kindness of the Prince of Robecq; begs that measures may be taken to obtain his release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Pigault de Lepinoy, President ----
    No monument worthy of Franklin's greatness; the objects which have aided him in his career will assume to the possessor a precious importance; an engraving of Franklin, a pair of spectracles and one of the pens which traced the glory and safety of America -- these represent his heart's desire; will Franklin refuse them to him?
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 11; A.L.S. 2p.; St. Clair, -----
    Innocent of the charge for which he has been confined during three months; had nothing to do with the arrest of the Captain of the Dutch corsair; persuaded if Franklin explains the affair to Comte de Ségur, there will be an end to his imprisonment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 12; L.S. 2p.; Macatter, Mary and A Kelly
    Acquainting Franklin with the distressing situation of their husbands, Capt. Edward Macatter and Capt. John Kelly ( alias Grumly); the former a prisoner in London, the latter in Dublin; money owing them from the sale of prizes by John Torris; the villainy and deceit of Torris; if the liquidation of the prizes could be obtained, something might be done; beg Franklin to intercede on their behalf.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Asking for a commission to command a letter of marque for Capt. Thomas Bell, commander of the "Renette" bound from l'Orient to Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Bouchet, -----. Paris
    Asks for a packet of clothing for Madame Williams at Nantes; his carriage commodious; will bear anything Franklin would like to send.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 15; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Carroll, John (Catholic Priest)
    Franklin may remember him by the campaign into Canada; begs that the enclosed letters may be forwarded.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Beall, Samuel. Williamsburg
    At Mrs. [Ann] Evans's request, encloses letters and bill of exchange for her daughter, Mrs. [Ann] Loviel; Mrs. Evans's strong desire to have her daughter back in Virginia; has promised to pay Mrs. Loviel's passage to the Captain of any vessel who will take her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Beall, Samuel. Williamsburg
    At the desire of Mrs.[Ann] Evans, asks Dr. Franklin to assist her daughter, Mrs. [Ann] Loviel, to return from France to Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 17; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Schwediauer, Francis Xavier
    Is a physician from Vienna and a fellow-traveler of Dr. Ingen Housz in his last journey to England; desires to communicate a plan for a code of penal laws, which might prove useful to any nation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 17; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Pierres, Philippe Denis
    Sending a copy of the Manual of Epictetus, in Greek, which he is at present printing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Barry, Amelia. Pisa
    Introducing Dr. Burrows; to her great regret, he and his family are going to England; any attention Franklin may show him she will consider as a personal favor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 21; L. in 3d. P. 1p.; Perregaux, -----. Paris
    Begging the acceptance of a bill of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. Nathaniel Nelson; his reason for going to Ireland; begs Franklin to grant him the necessary passport.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Brongniart, Antoine Louis. Paris
    Obtained from the sculptor he mentioned to Franklin two drawings of fair-sized medals, and two designs of the same subject from a painter of his acquaintance; desires to know when and where he can show them to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 Setember 23; A.L.S. 1P.; Nesbitt, Johnthan. L'Orient
    Seconding the request of Captains [Alexander] Cain, [James] Josiah and [Richard] Deale, of the ships "St. James," "Lady Washington" and "Queen of France."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 Setember 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Proposing a speedy method of exchanging a number of prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 Setember 25; A.L.S. 2p.; De Louse, Jean-Baptiste
    Begging for a passport for a vessel sailing from Ostend.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. Has no authority to give such passports, and if he had, it would be no of use.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 Setember 25; Lincoln, Benjamin.War Office, Phila
    Ordered by Congress to prepare and lay before them a state of the pay, rations and subsistence of the officers and men in the European armies; begs Franklin to furnish him with such details concercing the armies of France, Spain and Germany. Fine condition of the American army; compliment paid the troops by Count [de] Rochambeau; splendid conduct of the French troops; friendship existing between the two allied armies.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IX, 413).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 Setember 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Petit, -----. Paris
    M. de Villiers has constructed a watch on original lines; desires to place this invention before him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 Setember 30; A.L.S. 4P.; Barclay, Thomas. Brest
    Concerning the American supplies at Brest and the scarcity of proper vessels in which to carry, them; does not advise shipping any of them as long as there is a probability of the Court of France sending them; necessity of getting them off in time for the next campaign.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 September; Mem. 1p.; ------, ------
    Account of the daily consumption of wine, beer, etc., at Dr. Franklin's table.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 1; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Whitefoord, Caleb and Richard Oswald
    Promising to dine with Franklin; sending the letter relative to Capt. Blair; hope a favourable answer to Gen. Conway's request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Ridley, Matthew. Paris
    Concerning bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Found an account of Père Barletti's pamphlet in an Italian journal, Hopes Franklin has not laid aside his reflections on the new fire-place which has the form of a vase or urn. Trusts his admonition will have some effect on Mr. Samuel Wharton and his son. Message sent by Sir Robert Murray Keith to the Dutch Envoy at Vienna, to the effect that seven of the thirteen American provinces had submitted to the English government; desires to know whether there is any foundation for such a report. New and important discoveries he has made in vegetables. Experiment of burning wire.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 2; A.L.S. 4p.; Valltravers, Johann Rodolph. Vienna
    All his attempts to recover his sacrificed property from the German vultures have failed. Expects to leave shortly for Venice where he will be happy to receive Franklin's commands; thinks he might be useful in sounding the general disposition of the Venetian state towards America, and in bringing them over to the support of their sister-republic. Grants of land made to him in New York and Georgia. His belief in legal and equal liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Ponteney, comtesse de
    Had the honor of dining with Franklin four years before, on the eve of her departure for Italy; has just returned, bringing a letter in her favor from the Queen of Italy to the Queen of France; expects to go to Passy the following day for her answer, and begs permission to spend the time she may have to wait at Franklin's house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 4; L. in 3d P. 1p.; The Ambassador of the Emperor of H.R.E
    Will forward the package addressed to Mr. Ingen Housz, which Franklin has sent him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Acknowledging his of the 30th ult., with the enclosures for Captains [Alexander] Cain, [James] Josiah and [Richard] Deale, who are extremely obliged. Begs Franklin to order everything done to accelerate the speedy condemnation of the prize ship "Lion." Three American ships of force in port, which will sail for Philadelphia between the 15th and 20th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Wright, Patience. London
    Heard with great concern of his illness. Entertaining time she had at Bath.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Fort, Marc. Marseilles
    Requesting him to use his interest with Congress to obtain indemnity for them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 8; A.L.S. 4p.; Barclay, Thomas. Brest
    Impossibility of forwarding the supplies at the expense of the French Court; suggests various channels by which they may be shipped. News of the arrival at Boston of Capt. Grinnell with 2,500 suits of clothing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    After five months of travel and work has returned to the Countess of Forbach; regret to hear his health is not what it was; delighted to hear of the rich prizes lately brought in at l'Orient.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Regnier, ------. Paris
    Making a collection of the laws of the United States; his first volume presented to the Due de la Rochefoucauld, who approved his design of publishing a second volume; desires permission to copy certain documents which may not be in his collection and to submit the order and plan of his work to Franklin's criticism and advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Glad Franklin is better; can't afford to lose him yet. Has been promised that the 120 American prisoners should be sent to l'Orient as soon as a vessel could be got ready. Money he advanced to Capt. Houston before he left Forton Prison; desires to know if the bill will be honored in l'Orient; if so, wishes the money sent to Mr. Wright for the picture which he is expecting. Question of the French Ministry continuing the war after America's claims have been adjusted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 14; N. 1p.; Chalut and Arnous, Abbés
    Sending four letters of recommendation for Sir [Edward] Newenham.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Preble, Joshua. Tenterden
    Had the misfortune to be captured by the "Intrepid" while serving as captain of the sloop "Retaliation"; at present is on parole; begs Franklin to loan him ten or twelve pounds; his father is Jedediah Preble of Falmouth, and one of the Council of Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Washington, George. Head Quarters, State of New York
    Acknowledging Franklin's favors of April 2d and 8th delivered to him by the Comte de Ségur and the Prince de Brogile; promise of attention to these distinguished young noblemen. Reasons for fearing a continuance of their present troubles. Condition of military affairs.
    (Duplicate.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IX, 421; Bigelow, VIII, 199).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 18; L.S. 2p.; Niebelschütz, Capt. Wesel
    Desiring news of Frantz Siegfried de Wutsen, a resident of Magdeburg, who passed from the Prussian to the American service and embarked for the United States in 1777; since then his family have heard nothing of him; importance of ascertaining whether he be alive or dead.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 18; A.L. in 3d P. 2p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    Desiring him to forward the enclosed packet; it is the property of M. St. Jean de Crevecoeur, who desires particularly to know if Franklin received a work he sent him on the troubles and disasters of America.
    E. by M. de Musset-Pathay concerning the Comtesse d'Houdetot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 18; L.S. 1p.; Girardot, Haller and Co. Paris
    Introducing Mr. Housberg, head of a cast-iron foundry, whose proposals they trust will meet with Franklin's approval.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 20; L.S. 3p.; Penet, P. Belfort
    Obliged to suspend payment and to go into retirement; is trying to come to some agreement with his crediters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Auer, M. Ebingen
    Thanking him for his generous section on behalf of the widow Höcklerin; desires to know how she is to obtain the sum of money and how much it will be in the coin of the Realm.
    (In Fench.)
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. The sum is in the hands of M. Frederic Grand; Mrs. Höcklerin can draw it in such a manner as she shall be advised.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Bingel, R. Hoymb
    Concerning the estate of Johann Gottfried Schmidt. His son, Johann Friedrich, settled as preacher in Germantown, Pennsylvania, 15 years ago.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Crespin, Jacques François. Dunkirk
    The unfortunates who served on the "Revenge," Capt. Conyngham, disappointed again and again in the hope of obtaining their share of the prize-money; in danger at present of being turned into the street; begs Franklin to intercede with Mr. Richard Bache to procure their just dues.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October 24; L.S. 3p.; Calhoun, James
    Capt. Harrison's protest against the misconduct of the commander of the frigate "Em[e]r(o) [au]d[e]," whose desertion at a critical moment caused his ship the "Jolly Tar" to be taken by the English and carried to New York; detailed account of the whole affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 October; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Barney, Capt Joshua. Paris
    Accepting invitation for dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1782. October.]; Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple
    Oath of office as Secretary of the Commissioners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 1; L.S. 1p.; Cuming and Macarty. L'Orient
    Return Capt. Houston's bill accepted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 4; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Chalut and Arnous, Abbés
    Sending him the answer received from the Commandant of Lyons. [See XXVI, 48] in regard to their letter of recommendation to Sir [Edward] Newenham.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 6; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Ridley, Matthew. Paris
    Will wait upon Franklin the following Saturday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 6; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Chalut and Arnous, Abbés
    Desiring him to lend them the two volumes of Chinese memoirs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 7; L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Blancherie, Claude-Mammès de Pahin Champlain de
    Desires the death certificate of M. de Troye, Lieutenant in Pulaski's Legion, who died at Charlestown and was buried there on December 21st, 1779; also wishes Mr. [John] Adam's address.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Vicq d' Azyr, Félix
    Has been asked to write an eulogy on the late Sir John Pringle, to be read at their next public meeting [of the Royal Society of Medicine]; knowing this celebrated physician to have been a great friend of Franklin applies to him for details of his life and works.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Trumbull, Jonathan. Lebanon
    Reminds him of the circumstances of the institution of the University of Dartmouth in New Hampshire; Dr. [Eleazar] Wheelock's indefatigable labors to civilize and christianize the native Indians; this work interrupted by the war; Dr. Wheelock's son [John] now the president, who, in order to bring the institution to perfection, is authorized by the trustees to solicit benefactions in France and Holland; recommends him to Franklin's assistance and patronage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 10; A.L.S. 3p.; La Société Typographique
    A subscriber to their encyclopaedia of 39 volumes; by this time he will have received all the volumes, therefore they beg him to send the price of the subscription to M. Grand, banker in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Marseilles
    Fears that the British Janus does not intend to deal fairly by the Kingdom of Ireland in the expected treaty of peace; wishes to know if Ireland is particularly mentioned; has written a public letter to the men of Ireland advising them to demand this of their King; encloses a copy [1 p.]; has delayed sending it until he hears from Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Marseilles
    Nothing very interesting in Irish polities; Lord Temple more assiduous and more prodigal in offers to corrupt the Parliament than any of his predecessors. The British Ministry determined to push the raising of 5,000 fencibles. Respect and admiration for Franklin. Expects to convey to Ireland the valuable present of Franklin's bust, from which he expects to have many models made.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Marseilles
    Recommending Mr. John Christopher Hornbostel for Chief Consul for Provence and Languedoc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Delay in exchange caused by the Goverment having no ships for that service. Asked to propose to Franklin to exchange Lieut.-Col. Tarleton for two Captains of American privateers; England's attitude in hitherto absolutely refusing to acknowledge any rank in Americans taken and brought into England; thinks this proposition is due to the Heir-Apparent at the instigation of a beautiful lady who bestows her favors occasionally on both him and Lieut.-Col.-----; Mr. [Henry] Laurens returned from Bath and intends going to Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 14; L in 3d P. 1p.; Panckouche, Charles Joseph
    Sending him the enclosed letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 14; L.S. 2p.; Racine, Charles Quentin
    Served on the "Bon Homme Richard" under Paul Jones, when he captured the "Serapis"; demands his share of the prize-money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 16; L in 3d P. 1p.; Ehet, Johann Thadeus de
    The independence of the United States will shortly be recognized by all the powers of Europe; offers his services at Augsburg, in matters of politics, commerce, and jurisprudence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 16; A.L.S. 4p.; Ehet, Johann Thadeus de
    An Agent or chargé d'Affaires for the United States will be needed at every large German city. Offers his services.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 16; L in 3d P. 2p.; Pio, Luigi de
    Desiring to know if Franklin received a letter from M. Filangieri of Naples, the author of an essay on legislation, 1 who wishes to merit the esteem of the greatest philosopher of the New World.
    1 Scienza della Legislazione, Naples, 1780.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Carmichael, William. Madrid
    Introducing the Comte de Rechteien.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 21; A.L.S. 3p.; de Malsonneuve-Dommartin,------. Nancy
    Informed that History of the Revolution has been written in America; desires to know where he may obtain a copy; being prevented from fighting for the Colonies, wishes to render them a service by translating this history into French.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 22; A.L.S. 4p.; Cohin and Cie
    Have been defrauded by M. P. Penet; the merchandise supplied at his request was destined for Virginia, therefore they apply to Franklin, as the representative of the United States in France, to obtain payment for these goods.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 23; 4p.; Nepean, Sir Evan
    Papers and letters relative to complaints of the treatment of British prisoners in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Penn, Lady Juliana. London
    Begging his assistance and protection in recovering the rights and possessions of an unfortunate family; he knows their losses too well to need an account of them; aware that Lord Shelburne has authorized Mr. [Samuel] Vaughan to back her application, but would rather rely on the justice of her cause; adopts Franklin for the guardian of William Penn's grandchildren.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Fanning, Nathaniel. Dunkirk Gaol
    His arrest and imprisonment on the charge that his crew pillaged a neutral vessel; disclaims any knowledge of it; declares the orders on his vessel ["The Eclipse"] were very strict against plundering neutral vessels; thinks a captain cannot always prevent such unlawful proceedings; comes of a reputable family in New London; feels his character much injured by such treatment; implores Franklin's intercession on his behalf.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Arnauld, -----. Belleville
    As the director of a school intended for young noblemen, begs Franklin to recommend it to the Americans who intend educating their children in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 26; Pigott, Robert. Geneva
    Saw Franklin's grandson and his companion Jeanet; praises both boys.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, II. 227.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Anxious about Mr. Samuel Wharton's principles; cannot believe his crime is a worse one than a neglect to write; Dr. Bancroft's behavior inspires him with the most unfavorable suspicions; reasons why he can ill afford to lose any more money; begs Franklin to obtain from Mr. Bancroft, Mr. Wharton's original letters, look them over and report on them. Result of his controversy with Dr. Priestley; will follow Franklin's good advice about abstaining from polemics.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Des Rosières, -----
    Begging a passage to America for a clever youth called Minet; the sooner he leaves paris the better; his ability will enable him to become a printer or engage in any other work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Captain Geo[rge] Meggs, taken prisoner on his passage from New York to London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 November 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Ingenhousz, Jan